Guide to the Joan Kahn Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Joan Kahn papers
1945-1994
YCAL MSS 247
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.92
(8 boxes)
The Joan Kahn Papers document her work as a suspense book editor in New York City and largely consist of correspondence and dust jackets spanning from 1945 to 1989. Correspondence includes letters from: Jacques Barzun, Maurice Procter, and Julian Symons. Also included are other papers (such as notes for a business trip) dating from 1964 and 1975.
Kahn, Joan
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Olivia Kahn, 1995-1996.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Joan Kahn (1914-1994)
Joan Kahn was an editor of suspense novels and worked at firms including Harper and Row, Ticknor and Fields, Dutton, and St. Martin's Press during a career that spanned over forty years. Kahn also wrote two novels ( To Meet Miss Long and Open House ) and four children's books as well as edited eleven mystery anthologies.
Born in New York City, Kahn attended the Horace Mann School and pursued post-secondary education at the Yale School of Art, Barnard College and the Art Students' League. In 1946 Kahn began her career at Harper Brothers where she initially edited books about history, art, theater, and travel before starting the Harper Novels of Suspense Department. In the 1960s Kahn had her own imprint ("Joan Kahn Books") and the Mystery Writers of America awarded her the Ellery Queen Award and the Edgar Allan Poe Award in recognition of her distinguished career in publishing. Kahn died in New York City at the age of eighty in 1994.
Scope and Contents
The Joan Kahn Papers document her work as a suspense book editor in New York City and largely consist of correspondence and dust jackets spanning from 1945 to 1989. Also included are Kahn's personal papers dating from 1964 and 1975.
Arrangement
The Joan Kahn Papers are organized into the following three series: Correspondence, Other Papers, and Dust Jackets.
Book editors; Suspense fiction; Women editors -- United States; Book jackets; Editors; Barzun, Jacques, 1907-2012; Kahn, Joan; Procter, Maurice, 1906-; Symons, Julian, 1912-1994; Harper & Row, Publishers
- Correspondence, 1945-1989; Series I; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into two subseries: incoming and outgoing correspondence. Both are arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Kahn's professional correspondence. Among her correspondents are authors she published as well as fans (including Bess and Harry Truman and John F. Kennedy).
  - Incoming
    - Abrahamsen, David, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "B" General, 1964-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Barzun, Jacques, 1969-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "C" General, 1965, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Carvic, Heron, 1970, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cecil, Henry, 1960-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Day Lewis, C. (Cecil), 1954-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Also contains a limited edition typescript copy of "The Newborn" by D.M.B. dated 1957 April 29 (inscribed to Kahn)
    - Dickinson, Peter, 1969-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Doohey, Brigitte, 1988 January 13 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Escott, Jonathan, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes one letter from Peter Escott
    - Fordham, Peta, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Francis, Dick, 1969-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Freeling, Nicolas, 1963-1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "G" General, 1982, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Gallie, Menna, 1960-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes enclosed letter in Welsh to Menna Gallie from publisher Hughes A'I Fab. Also includes two letters from Gallie's husband Bryce Gallie
    - Gilbert, Michael, 1953-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Grant, John, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "H" General, 1964-1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Halls, Geraldine, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Hardinge, George, 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Hillerman, Tony, 1971, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "J" General, 1945, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Jhabvala, Ruth Prawer, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Johnson, E. Richard (Emil Richard), 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Kuh, Katharine, 1964, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "L" General, 1963, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Langton, Jane, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Lolos, Kimon, 1963-1974 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Maling, Arthur, 1978-1979, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - McAdoo, Richard B., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - McClure, James, 1973-1982 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - McGinley, Patrick, 1987, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Moses, Robert, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "N" General, 1979, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "P" General, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Procter, Maurice, 1953, 1960, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - "R" General, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Rawson, Clayton, 1970 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1962 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - "S" General, 1965-1986 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Symons, Julian, 1964-1987 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Truman, Bess Wallace, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Truman, Harry, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - "V" General, 1966 January 25 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - "W" General, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Wesker, Arnold, 1967-1978 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Winterton, Paul, 1960-1971 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Wynd, Oswald, 1969-1987 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - "Z" General, 1978 June 23 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Unidentified, 1964-1984, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Other Papers, 1964-1994; Series II; 4
  The series is arranged in chronological order.
  The series contains material relating to Kahn's work as an editor dating from roughly 1964 to 1975. Also included is the Program for Joan Kahn's memorial service in 1994.
  - Business trip materials, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Publicity materials for Patrick McGinley's Bogmail, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Net sales list, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Program for Joan Kahn's memorial service, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Dust Jackets, 1946-1990; Series III; 2.29; (6 boxes)
  The series is arranged alphabetically by author and book title. Book jackets are filed under authors' published name, with pseudonyms cross-referenced where applicable.
  The series contains dust jackets from a number of books Kahn published dating largely from the late 1940s to the 1980s. The dust jackets are of particular interest because Kahn found her own jacket artists (including her sister Olivia Kahn) and wrote her own jacket copy.
  - Alding, Peter, circa 1967 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Ashford, Jeffrey
  - Ashford, Jeffrey, 1960-1964 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    See also: Alding, Peter
  - Atiyah, Edward Selim, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Atkins, Meg Elizabeth, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Audemars, Pierre, 1961, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Ballinger, Bill S. (Bill Sanborn), 1955, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Bax, Roger, 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    See also: Garve, Andrew
    See also: Somers, Paul
  - Black, Gavin, 1966-1975 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Blaisdell, Anne, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    See also: Egan, Lesley
    See also: Linington, Elizabeth
    See also: Shannon, Dell
  - Blake, Nicholas, 1949, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Bodelsen, Anders, 1969-1976 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Borgenicht, Miriam, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Borneman, Ernest, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Boston, Robert, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Brock, Rose, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Browne, Courtney, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Burke, J.F., 1976 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Calvin, Henry, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Carr, John Dickson, 1952, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Carvic, Heron, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Cashman, John, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Cleife, Philip, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Colton, Jennifer, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Cores, Lucy Michaella, 1951, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Creasey, John, 1948-1954 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Dessart, Gina, 1947-1959 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Dickinson, Peter, 1970, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Dobyns, Stephen, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Douglass, Donald McNutt, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Downey, Bridgitte, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Dunn, Dorothy, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Dwight, Olivia, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Egan, Lesley, 1961-1972 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    See also: Blaisdell, Anne
  - Erhlich, May, 1952, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Eustis, Helen, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Femling, Jean, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Fenwick, Elizabeth, 1957, 1958, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Fisher, Hope, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Fitt, Mary, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Fordham, Peta, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Freeling, Nicholas, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Friedman, Mickey, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Gallie, Menna, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Garve, Andrew, 1951-1971 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    See also: Bax, Roger
  - Gash, Jonathon, 1983-1990 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Gethin, David, 1983, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Gilbert, Harriett, 1976, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Gilbert, Michael Francis, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Greenbaum, Leonard, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - Gulik, Robert Hans van, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Haddad, C.A., 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - Hamilton, Bruce, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - Hardin, Peter, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Hardy, Lindsay, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Hildick, Wallace, 1975, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - Holden, Anne, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - Hough, Richard Alexander, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Innes, Hammond, 1947-1950 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Jackson, Clarence J.L., 1973 (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Jay, Charlotte, 1961, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Jepson, Selwyn, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Johnson, E. Richard, 1968-1971 (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - Kahn, E. J. (Ely Jacques), 1973 (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - Kahn, Joan, 1946-1987 (Box 6, Folder 121-122)
  - Kapralov, Yuri, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - Krasner, William, 1950, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Kuttner, Henry, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 125)
  - Lacy, Ed, 1956-1966 (Box 6, Folder 126-127)
  - Langton, Jane, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 128)
  - Leonard, Frank, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 129)
  - Linington, Elizabeth, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 130)
  - Lobell, N. D. (Nathan D.), 1949 (Box 6, Folder 131)
  - Lolos, Kimon, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 132)
  - Longrigg, Roger, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 133)
  - Lyon, Mabel Dana, 1950-1958 (Box 6, Folder 134)
  - Maling, Arthur, 1970-1979 (Box 6, Folder 135-136)
  - Mallet, Jacqueline, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 137)
  - Marble, M. S. (Margaret Sharp), 1947 (Box 6, Folder 138)
  - Marric, J. J., 1971, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 139)
  - Maxfield, Henry S., 1958 (Box 6, Folder 140)
  - McGinley, Patrick, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 141)
  - McMullen, Mary, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - Mornell, Pierre, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 143)
  - Mosley, Leonard, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 144)
  - Olmstead, Alan H., 1975 (Box 7, Folder 145)
  - Pace, Tom, 1969-1971 (Box 7, Folder 146)
  - Perowne, Barry, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 147)
  - Pettit, Paul, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 148)
  - Piper, Evelyn, 1956, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 149)
  - Player, Robert, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 150)
  - Procter, Maurice, 1951-1968 (Box 7, Folder 151-152)
  - Prou, Suzanne, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 153)
  - Reno, Marie R., 1976 (Box 7, Folder 154)
  - Resnicow, Herbert, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 155)
  - Rieman, Terry, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 156)
  - Roman, Howard, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 157)
  - Roueché, Berton, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 157)
  - Scott, Jack S., 1976-1985 (Box 7, Folder 158-159)
  - Shannon, Dell, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 160)
  - Shimer, R. H. (Ruth H.), 1972 (Box 7, Folder 161)
  - Smith, Bridget A., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 162)
  - Smith, Shelley, 1947-1962 (Box 8, Folder 163-165)
  - Somers, Paul, 1958-1961 (Box 8, Folder 166)
  - Symons, Julian, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 167)
  - Tallant, Robert, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 168)
  - Tate, Sylvia, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 169)
  - Thompson, Jim, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 170)
  - Thomson, June, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 171)
  - Travers, Hugh, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 172)
  - Trevor, Elleston, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 173)
  - Warren, Joyce, 1957, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 174)
  - White, Reginald James, 1961-1971 (Box 8, Folder 175)
  - Williams, Alan, 1963, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 176)
  - Williams, Vinnie, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 177)
  - Wise, Arthur, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 178)
  - Wolfe, Michael, 1973-1976 (Box 8, Folder 179)
  - Wolfe, Winifred, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 180)
  - Woodfin, Henry, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 181)
  - Woods, Sara, 1965-1968 (Box 8, Folder 182)
  - Youd, Samuel, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 183)
  - Young, Edward Preston, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 184)